Inventory of the Fakhreddin Moussavi papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Fakhreddin Moussavi papers
1974-1981
81086
Moussavi, Fakhreddin, 1940-
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers include the creator's dissertation, along with newspapers, clippings, serial publications, booklets, and other writings relating to education in Iran, the Iranian revolution of 1979, and political, social, and economic conditions in Iran.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Fakhreddin Moussavi was born in Iran in 1940. In the years following, the country experienced a flood of political events including the British embargo on Iranian oil exports and the Shah's 1963 "White Revolution." During the 1979 Iranian Revolution, and the subsequent formation of the Islamic Republic of Iran, Fakhreddin Moussavi attended Stanford University, where he earned his PhD. His dissertation, published in 1980, focused on elementary-level social studies education in Iran. In this same year, Abolhasan Banisadr was elected the first president of the Islamic Republic of Iran and the Iran-Iraq war had commenced (BBC News, 2009).
Arrangement
The collection is organized in 2 series based on the creator's original order and physical format of material.
Scope and Content of Collection
The content of this collection was gathered by Fakhreddin Moussavi as he attended graduate school in the United States. The newspaper clippings cover events and figures of the Iranian revolution, including the revision of the Iranian Constitution and the election of Abolhasan Banisadr, the first president of the Islamic Republic of Iran. Relations between Iran and Iraq, literary events featuring various authors and professors, as well as clippings on social and economic conditions in Iran are represented in the Newspapers and Clippings series.
The Research Materials series includes three occasional publications from the International Council for Educational Development. These booklets, along with other reports, focus on the state of higher education in the United States and Iran. Some of these materials convey a broad survey of the system while others provide detailed insight into the changes in the education system from the final years of the Shah's reign to immediately after the Ayatollah Khomeini's religious referendum. Moussavi's dissertation, written at Stanford University, on elementary-level social studies programs in Iran is included in the collection, alongside other college-level papers.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Education--Iran.; Iran--History--1979-
Collection Contents
- Newspaper Clippings and Newspapers, 1975-1981 (Box 1-2)
  Clippings discuss social, economic, and political conditions in Iran. Iranian newspapers, printed in the United States, cover current events and political news in Iran between 1979 and 1981. Clippings are arranged in alphabetical order by subject matter, as defined by the creator of the collection. Newspapers are arranged by title and year.
  - Clippings, 1975-1981 (Folder 1)
    - Archaeology and Historical Monuments, 1976-1977 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Books, Reading, and Libraries, 1976-1978 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Countries and Cities of the World, 1978 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Culture and Civilization, 1977-1978 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Economics: Iran and the World, 1975-1980 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Education, 1976-1978 (Folder 1: 6)
    - History, 1977 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Iranian Cities, 1976-1978 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Literature and Literary Figures, 1976-1978 (Folder 1: 9)
    - People of the World, 1975 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Politics: Iran and the World, 1976-1981 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Population: Iran and the World, 1976-1977 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Printing (Trade), 1977 (Folder 1: 13)
    - Religion, 1976-1980 (Folder 1: 14)
    - Silk Worm and Silk, 1977 (Folder 1: 15)
    - Technology, 1977 (Folder 1: 16)
    - Terrorism, 1980 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Urbanization, 1978 (Folder 1: 18)
    - Women and Education, 1977-1980 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Newspapers, 1980-1981 (Folder 1-2)
    - Iran Times (English), 2 February-18 December, 1979 (Folder 1: 20)
    - Iran Times (English), 4 January-4 July, 1980 (Folder 1: 21)
    - Iran Tribune, 12 July-27 September, 1980 (Folder 1: 22)
    - Iran Tribune, 4 October-22 November, 1980 (Folder 1: 23)
    - Pardis, 18 July, 1981 (Folder 1: 24)
    - Etlyah'at, serial publication, 1980 (Folder 2: 1)
- Research Materials and Writings, 1974-1981 (Box 2-3)
  Fakhreddin Moussavi's graduate dissertation at Stanford, titled Social Studies Programs in Iranian Elementary and Secondary Schools, begins the Education subseries, followed by other articles, writings, and reports on the state of education in Iran and the world. Other sociopolitical writings on human rights in Iran and elementary-level workbooks are included in the Culture and Society subseries. Arranged into two subseries, Education and Culture and Society.
  - Education, 1974-1980 (Folder 2-3)
    - Social Studies Programs in Iranian Elementary and Secondary Schools (Dissertation), 1980 (Folder 2: 2-3)
    - Education Outside Iran, booklets, surveys, and reports, 1974-1976 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Education Questionnaires, 1979-1980 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Higher Education, reports, June, 1975-January, 1978 (Folder 3: 1-3)
    - Elementary Level, workbooks, 1975-1976 (Folder 3: 4)
    - College Coursework, 1976-1978 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Culture and Society, 1975-1981 (Folder 3)
    - Human Rights in Iran, 1981 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Sociology in Iran, article, 1975 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Profile of Iran, serial publications, 1977 (Folder 3: 8)